Kansas City Southern Railways Company 1933 Strike Miscellany 5601
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Kansas City Southern Railways Company 1933 Strike Miscellany
1921-1934
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Kansas City Southern Railways (KCS)
5601
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Scrapbook titled: "Kansas City Southern Plans for Conductors, Firemen, Yardmen." Contains documentation of the Kansas City Southern Railways Strike of 1933.
5675101
Biographical / Historical
The Kansas City Southern Railway [KCS] is a Class 1 railroad operating in the United States and Mexico. The KCS was founded in 1887 in Kansas City, Missouri by Arthur E. Stilwell. The KCS expanded their holdings in the following decade through the acquisition of the Arkansas Western Railway Company and the Texarkana and Fort Smith Railway Company. The KCS successfully linked Kansas City with the Gulf of Mexico at its terminus in Port Arthur, Texas, which was named after Arthur Stilwell.
KCS and its employees had been operating under series of contracts between the carrier and the various crafts and classes that had been in effect since 1924-1925. On January 1, 1932, both the carrier and the unions had entered, with 130 other American railroads and the unions, into what was called the "Chicago Agreement." The Chicago Agreement was a measure designed by President Roosevelt and his administration to help lift America out of the Great Depression in which the wage rates of employees would remain unchanged, but the railroads could deduct ten percent from each employee's pay check for a period of one year, provided the railroads did all in their power to maintain or even increase their number of employees. This wage reduction was part of a broader trend of wage reductions, in order to try and kickstart the American economy. At the end of this year, a wage dispute arrose between KCS and its employees.
According to the U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics, "An emergency board to investigate the wage dispute between the Kansas City Southern Railway and its engineers, firemen, conductors, and trainmen, was appointed on June 12, 1933. The carrier and these employees were parties to the so-called "Chicago agreement" of January 31, 1932, which provided for a 10-percent deduction from the wages of the employees during the year beginning February 1, 1932. On December 31, 1932, the agreement was extended to October 31, 1933, on most of the railroads. The Kansas City Southern Railway Co. was not a party to the extension agreement, but continued to make the 10 percent deduction under the terms of a mediation agreement entered into February 23, 1933. On April 5, 1933, the carrier served notice of cancelation, on May 15, 1933, of all contracts covering rates of pay, rules, and working conditions. On April 6, 1933, it declared its intention of placing in effect on May 16, 1933, new rates of pay, rules, and working conditions. Conferences and mediation were unsuccessful, and on June 6, 1933, the employees voted overwhelmingly to strike.
On July 12, 1933, the emergency board reported its findings, pointing out the employees' belief that acceptance of the company's demands would mean 'a complete breakdown of the many years of efforts of organized railroad labor and would be and become an opening wedge toward the ultimate breakdown of these conditions upon all the other railroads in this country.' In deference to the wish of President [Roosevelt] 'for peace between labor and employer while the country is trying to regain prosperity,' expressed in a letter to [the KCS] president, the carrier postponed putting into effect the proposed new schedule until early in 1934, continuing in the meantime under the existing rates of pay, rules, and working conditions" (Handbook of Labor Statistics, 1936 Edition, Issue 616, pp. 22-23).
In 1934, the same issues arose between KCS and their employees. President Roosevelt dispatch Joseph B. Eastman, Federal Coordinator of Transportation, to mediate between the parties. The strike was once again postponed while the parties submitted themselves to mediation.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1921-1932
Bulk dates: 1932-1934
This collection contains documentation of a wage dispute between the Kansas City Southern Railways [KCS] and their employees represented by the "Big Four" railroad brotherhoods: the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers [BLE]; the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen [BLF&E]; the Order of Railway Conductors [ORC]; and the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen [BRT].
The records in this collection document the wages of employees who were members of one of the Big Four as well as how those wages would be affected by a proposed change to wage schedules by KCS management. Reactions to these changes from the union representatives, employees, and various managers are found in both correspondence and in pamphlets printed by both sides of the dispute to try to influence public opinion. The wage schedules are heavily annotated to show how the wages for the employees would fall should the KCS plan be put in place. Newspaper clippings documenting the negotiations are found in this collection. Of interest are the minutes of the meetings of the unions where the vast majority of the employees voted in favor of a strike and the correspondence between the grand chairmen of the Big Four, wherein they establish a series of code words to be used to verify the authenticity of any correspondence regarding a strike. Telegrams calling off the strike because of the intervention of the federal government are also found in the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
E. Parker, June 05, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, June 05, 2017
Railroads -- Kansas -- Kansas City; Strikes and lockouts -- Railroads -- Kansas -- Kansas City; Wages -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Kansas City Southern Railway; Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Eastman, Joseph B. (Joseph Bartlett), 1882-1944; Deramus, William Neal; Order of Railway Conductors of America; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.); Arkansas Western Railway Company; Texarkana & Fort Smith Railway Company; Delaware and Hudson Railroad Corporation; United States. Railway Labor Act
5675101
- "Kansas City Southern Plans for Conductors, Firemen, Yardmen" Index, 1921-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Table of contents on front cover, back cover annotated
- Schedule for Trainmen, submitted by C.E. Johnston, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  June 15, 1921
- Schedule for Brakemen, submitted by W. N. Deramus, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  November 17, 1932
- Schedule for Yardmen, submitted by W. N. Deramus, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Schedule for Firemen, submitted by W. N. Deramus, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Schedule for Conductors, submitted by W. N. Deramus, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Delaware and Hudson Railroad Schedule for Trainmen, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  August 1, 1932; letters attached
- Memorandum and letter transmittal W. N. Deramus, and other correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Regarding the Schedules for Brakemen and Yardmen (folders 3 and 4)
- Questions About Proposed KCS Plan, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  (In index, called "Questions TBL 2 and 3 above")
- Comparisons Schedule and KCS Plan, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  By Railway Company and by T. B. Leach
- Agreement required of clerks who work on enforced vacation days, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letter from H. E. Hennessey to T. B. Leach, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Loree's plan for saving millions, KCS Ry Magazine, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  January-February-March 1933 issue
- Miscellaneous telegrams from A. B. Cranor to T. B. Leach re strike, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  On index "Misc correspondence self and others, KCS plan"
- Tabulation of service of T. B. Leach as brakeman, May 1929 to November 1930, inclusive, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Strike ballot, minutes of the "Big Four" Grand Committee Meetings, strike instructions, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Minutes of "Big Four" Union meetings, Pittsburgh, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  June 13, 1933
- Postponement of strike, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- KCS Wage Plan Facts, by W. N. Deramus, general manager of KCS (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Letter and wage comparisons, from W. N. Deramus, to all ORC and BLE, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Answer to KCS propaganda pamphlet, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Letter from KCS to T. B. Leach, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  "Quit if don't advise will work after March 1, 1934"
- Circular "Why we are 100% for the KCS," by the 83% Club, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Published and paid for, by popular subscription, by members of the KCS 83% Club, a group representing 83% of Kansas City Southern employees."
- Circular letter to all train, engine, and yard men from the general chairmen of the "Big Four", 1934 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Newspaper clippings re strike, from various newspapers, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Correspondence and Alternatives to the KCS Plan furnished to all ORC and BLE by Company, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 26)